Abraham: Most people today carry a smart
phone, it is a way of communicating
with friends, watching and downloading
movies and TV series, catching up on news
stories, buying things online and booking
tickets for a range of different things.
It can also be used for playing games
and communicating with a variety
of other devices and appliances
around the home and at work.
For some people it is their only point of
contact as they no longer have a landline.
Nicole: There are lots of positives
for having a smart phone but there are
negatives that we have to consider.
As the number of mobile phone users around
the world soars mobile networks need to be
able to handle the immense demands on data
and how quickly they can access services.
The opportunity for cybercrime
increases as our dependency increases.
Mobile malware can target systems
due to unsecure usage of URL's
over WiFi or other networks.
Mobile users are at risk of spam
and other cybersecurity attacks.
We all know about those bogus SMS
messages asking us to click on a link.
Abraham: Let's start by looking
at the hype around 5G fifth
generation wireless network.
3G smartphones have download speeds
of approximately 2Mbps [megabits
per second], 4G is around 3-5Mbps.
Currently 5G is at least 3-6 times faster
than 4G but could reach up to 100-200Mbps
but this will depend on the providers
coverage and the areas a person is in.
As mobile network generations evolve
the speed and efficiency increases
and offers a great more opportunities
for connectivity and the use of IOT.
5G means gadgets will be more
efficient and therefore relied on
more but they will also be more
opportunities for cyber attacks.
There is also a lot of opposition to 5G
and conspiracy theories are increasing.
This opens opportunities for
anti 5G activists and a great
deal of false information.
Nicole: This level of connectivity
will be and to some extent is already
all around us, imagine fully connected
homes, vehicles and smart cities.
With this new connectivity and the
use of IOT devices, cyber security
is even more essential, as we rely
on this technology more, then the
need for it to be secure is greater.
Allowing devices to connect to
the internet opens them up to a
number of serious vulnerabilities
if they are not protected properly.
Application programme interface
or API security and public key
infrastructure, PKI authentication
are a few of the methods that can
be used to combat this threat.
Imagine if an electric car was
hacked what damage could be caused,
we have all seen this portrayed
in movies but it is a real threat.
Household devices run off the local area
networks and should be covered by the
router or hub's firewall security, but
mobile devices are a different matter.
It is all too easy for cyber criminals
to clone phones and credit card details
by just passing close to an individual.